Inventory of the Mihajlo Mihajlov papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Mihajlo Mihajlov papers
1921-2010
87076
Mihajlov, Mihajlo, 1934-2010
42 manuscript boxes, 23 oversize boxes (40 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The papers consist mostly of writings and research materials relating to political conditions and human rights in Yugoslavia and the Soviet Union, and to Russian literature. Additional materials include correspondence, printed matter, and sound and video recordings.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1987 with an addition in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Rusko Matulić papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Milovan Djilas writings, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
September 26, 1934 Born in Pančevo, Yugoslavia
1959 Graduated from Philosophy Faculty of Zagreb University
1961-1962 Served in the Yugoslav Army
1962-1963 Worked as translator and free-lance writer in Zagreb
1963 Assistant Professor of Russian literature and language at the Philosophy Faculty of the Zadar branch of Zagreb University
Summer 1964 Visited the Soviet Union as part of a Soviet-Yugoslav cultural exchange program and spent several weeks in Moscow and other Soviet cities
1965 Author, Moscow Summer
1966 Arrested and sentenced to jail for "slandering a friendly nation" with the publication of Moscow Summer Author, A Historical Perspective
1968 Author, Russian Themes
1970 Released from prison
1970-1974 Worked as free-lance writer in Novi Sad, contributed to the world press, and drafted Unscientific Thoughts
October 1974 Arrested for essays and articles published in the Western press
1975 Sentenced by the District Court at Novi Sad, Serbia, to seven years' imprisonment on charges of suspicion of hostile activity against Yugoslavia and spreading hostile propaganda, arising out of articles published in the West
1976 Author, Underground Notes
November 1977 Amnestied before the end of his term under the pressure of President Jimmy Carter's human rights campaign
1978 Moved to the United States; received an award from the International League for Human Rights for outstanding contribution to the promotion and protection of international human rights and justice
1978-1985 Taught courses in Russian literature and philosophy at several universities in the United States and Western Europe
1979 Author, Unscientific Thoughts
1980 Recipient of the Ford Foundation Award for Humanistic Perspectives on Contemporary Society
1985-1994 Worked for Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty as an analyst and commentator for intellectual and ideological affairs, in Munich and Washington, D.C.
1994-1999 Senior associate with the program on transitions to democracy, Elliot School of International Affairs, the George Washington University, Washington, D.C.
1999 Adjunct fellow of the Hudson Institute
2000 Visiting Professor at State University - Higher School of Economics in Moscow, Russia
2001-2010 Resided in Belgrade, published and lectured actively
2010 Died in Belgrade, Serbia
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Mihajlo Mihajlov, a prominent dissident and author in the former Yugoslavia who was jailed as a political prisoner during the Cold War, consist mostly of writings and research materials relating to political conditions and human rights in Yugoslavia and the Soviet Union, as well as Russian literature. The papers also include correspondence, biographical material, printed matter, and sound and visual recordings.
The Biographical file contains records of Mihajlov's career and family, as well as documents relating to his political trials. The Correspondence includes both personal and business correspondence. A significant number of letters are between Mihajlov and his family during his imprisonment. Charles, Prince of Wales, also showed interest in Mihajlov's case; copies of some of his letters are filed in the correspondence.
The Subject files on human rights and dissident movements were developed by Mihajlov throughout his career. The files also include extensive material on Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty.
Speeches and writings contain manuscript drafts of most of Mihajlov's books and articles, as well as copies of his numerous published articles and interviews in periodicals in the United States, Western Europe, and Serbia, including Russian and Serbian émigré newspapers in the United States. The writings also contain notes, drafts, and collected research materials regarding his doctoral dissertation on Russian literature.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into nine series: Biographical file, Correspondence, Subject file, Speeches and Writings, Writings about Mihajlov, Writings by Others, Card file, Oversize material, and Audiovisual recordings.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Radio Free Europe.; Soviet Union--Politics and government--1945-1991.; Civil rights--Soviet Union.; Yugoslavia--Politics and government--1945-; Civil rights--Yugoslavia.; Radio broadcasting--Europe, Eastern.; Dissenters--Yugoslavia.; Yugoslavs--United States.; Political prisoners--Yugoslavia.; Russian literature.; Phonotapes.; Videotapes.
Collection Contents
- Biographical file, 1935-2008 (Box 1-3)
  Includes identification cards, curriculum vitae, a bibliography, academic appointments, contact lists, photographs, and political trial documents.
  Arranged by physical form
  - General, 1935-2008 (Folder 1-2)
    - Identification documents, birth certificate copy, 1935; Yugoslavian citizenship copy, 1978; newspaper reporter permits, 1972-1973 (Folder 1: 1)
    - Biography, circa 1980 (Folder 1: 2)
    - Family history, 1962-1992 (Folder 1: 3)
    - "Background Report,", circa 1980 (Folder 1: 4)
    - Curriculum vitae, circa 1982-1992 (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - Biographical clippings from the 1976 World Book Year Book; Current Biography Yearbook, 1979; International Who's Who, 1994-2005; International Authors and Writers Who's Who, 1989 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Awards, 1998-1999 (Folder 1: 8)
    - Bibliography, 1965-1998 (Folder 1: 9-11)
    - Contacts, including address book, mailing and telephone lists; business cards, 1965-1998 (Folder 1: 12-13)
      See also Card file
    - Contacts, circa 1980 (Contd.) (Folder 2: 1-2)
    - Academic appointments, 1983-1990 (Folder 2: 3-6)
    - Publishing contracts, 1972-2008 (Folder 2: 7)
    - Photographs, depicting Mihajlo Mihajlov at various stages of his life and career, 1952-2002 (Folder 2: 8-12)
      Includes photos with Kurt Vonnegut, Vasilii Aksenov, Vladimir Bukovskii, Vladimir Voinovich, and others
    - Political trials documents, 1966-1975 (Folder 3: 1-6)
      Includes applications and rejections for employment, health insurance, and international passport, as well as clippings and articles
- Correspondence, 1965-2010 (Box 3-7)
  Arranged in two groups, general and alphabetical, the latter by name or organization
  - General, 1966-2008 (Folder 3-4)
    - Drafts, 1969-1976 (Folder 3: 7-8)
    - Unidentified, 1967-2006 (Folder 3: 9-13)
    - Invitations, 1966-2008 (Folder 3: 14)
    - Publishers, A-Z, 1970-2000 (Folder 4: 1)
    - Universities, 1964-2006 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Alphabetical, 1965-2010 (Folder 4-7)
    - A-Z, 1972-2006 (Folder 4: 3-6)
    - American Croatians for Human and National Rights, 1987 (Folder 4: 7)
    - Amnesty International, 1975-1980 (Folder 4: 8)
    - Arsen'ev, A., 2007 (Folder 4: 9)
    - Barbone, Donato, 1971-1972 (Folder 4: 10)
    - Barovic, Jovan, 1973-1975 (Folder 4: 11-12)
    - Barovic family, 2001-2010 (Folder 4: 13)
    - Beljajev, S., 1995-1997 (Folder 4: 14)
    - Belotserkovsky, Vadim, 1975-1978 (Folder 4: 15)
    - Bjelousov, A., 2004 (Folder 4: 16)
    - Bogunovic (Stambolic), Milici, 1973-2000 (Folder 5: 1-2)
    - Bonner, Elena, 1983 (Folder 5: 3)
    - "Borba,", 1974 (Folder 5: 4)
    - Chafee, Richard, 1972 (Folder 5: 5)
    - Chamraeff, V., 1974 (Folder 5: 6)
    - Charles, Prince of Wales, 1982-1988 (Folder 5: 7)
    - Congratulatory letters on Mihajlov's release from prison, 1978 (Folder 5: 8)
    - Cvetcovic, Dragomir, 1974 (Folder 5: 9)
    - Delo, 1965-1966 (Folder 5: 10)
    - DioGuardi, Shirley Cloyes, 2001 (Folder 5: 11)
    - Dole, Bob, 1991 (Folder 5: 12)
    - Dolinsek, Valerija, 1974-1975 (Folder 5: 13)
    - Fond, Kraljevski Dvor, 2005-2007 (Folder 5: 14)
    - Fosty, Vera, 1975 (Folder 5: 15)
    - Freedom House, 1972-1987 (Folder 5: 16)
    - Gesellschaft für Menschenrechte, 1977 (Folder 5: 17)
    - Glowatzky, Ivo, 1974-1975 (Folder 5: 18)
    - Goldstein, Slavko, 1974 (Folder 5: 19)
    - Graƌanski Savez Srbije, 1992 (Folder 5: 20)
    - Grkovic-Janovic, S., 2010 (Folder 5: 21)
    - Heritage Foundation, 1979 (Folder 5: 22)
    - Hoover Institution, 1972-1992 (Folder 5: 23)
    - Ivusic, Sean and Maureen, 2000-2001 (Folder 5: 24)
    - Japan UNI Agency, Inc., 1970-1973 (Folder 5: 25)
    - Jonasson, Lise-Lotte, 1970 (Folder 5: 26)
    - Jovanovic, T., 2000-2009 (Folder 5: 27)
    - Karadjordjevic, Aleksandar, 2005 (Folder 5: 28)
    - Kovacevic, Veljko, 1975 (Folder 5: 29)
    - Kuznetsov, Pavel, 1992 (Folder 5: 30)
    - Lembourn, Hans Jorgen, 1975, 1978 (Folder 5: 31)
    - Mackenzie, A., 2000 (Folder 5: 32)
    - Maksimov, Vladimir E., 1980-1983 (Folder 5: 33-34)
    - Mihajlov (Ivusic), Marija (sister), 1974-2010 (Folder 6: 1-3)
    - Mihajlov, Vera (mother), 1974-1981 (Folder 6: 4-16)
    - Mihajlov, Vera (mother), 1974-1981 (Contd.) (Folder 7: 1-6)
    - Nedenlans Publishing, Sweden, 1973 (Folder 7: 7)
    - New Leader, 1970-2007 (Folder 7: 8)
    - New York Times, 1970-1971 (Folder 7: 9)
    - Palavestra, P., 2005 (Folder 7: 10)
    - Pavloff, Vladko, 1975 (Folder 7: 11)
    - Pavlovskii, A., 1990 (Folder 7: 12)
    - P.E.N. club français, 1978 (Folder 7: 13)
    - Pejovic, D., 1974 (Folder 7: 14)
    - Petrovic, Nenand, 2001-2008 (Folder 7: 15)
    - Petrovic, Zdenka, 1975 (Folder 7: 16)
    - Pirozhkova, Vera, 1970 (Folder 7: 17)
    - Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty, 1987-1997 (Folder 7: 18)
    - Radmonovic, Liliana, 1975 (Folder 7: 19)
    - Rakauskaite, Violeta, 2002 (Folder 7: 20)
    - Ratinic, Marijan, 1969 (Folder 7: 21)
    - Ribi, Federica, 1974-1975 (Folder 7: 22)
    - Rogers, Robert J., 1965 (Folder 7: 23)
    - Ruffin, Richard, 1998 (Folder 7: 24)
    - Schwab, Andrea R., 2004-2007 (Folder 7: 25)
    - Siniavski, Andrei, 1973 (Folder 7: 26)
    - Smith, Charles B., 1973 (Folder 7: 27)
    - Solov'eva, Marina, 1996-1998 (Folder 7: 28)
    - Svirskii, Grigorii, 1984 (Folder 7: 29)
    - Vidovic, Mirko, 1970, 1978 (Folder 7: 30)
    - Zaslavskii, S. K., 1974 (Folder 7: 31)
- Subject file, 1967-2007 (Box 8-11)
  Contains correspondence, printed matter, manuscripts, and clippings.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Arsen'ev, Aleksei, 1992-2002 (Folder 8: 1)
  - Carter, Jimmy, 1977-1978 (Folder 8: 2)
  - Charles, Prince of Wales, 1982-2000 (Folder 8: 3-4)
  - Conferences, seminars, and symposiums on human rights in Yugoslavia, 1976-2007 (Folder 8: 5-13)
  - Dissident movement in Yugoslavia, 1975-2007 (Folder 9: 1-3)
  - Genis, Aleksandar, 1998 (Folder 9: 4)
  - Human rights, 1976-2000 (Folder 9: 5-6)
  - Kosovo, 1989-1999 (Folder 9: 7)
  - Mihajlov (Ivusic), Marija, 1968-1988 (Folder 9: 8)
  - Mihajlov, Vera, circa 1985-1993 (Folder 9: 9-10)
  - Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty, 1978-2001 (Folder 10: 1-15)
  - Russian immigration in Yugoslavia, 1989-2002 (Folder 11: 1)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1979-1980 (Folder 11: 2)
  - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr, 1962-1970 (Folder 11: 3)
  - Tito, Josip Broz, 1967-1979 (Folder 11: 4)
- Speeches and writings, 1961-2009 (Box 11-29)
  Consists of manuscripts, articles, and books.
  Arranged by physical form andchronologically therein
  - Manuscripts, 1966-2005 (Folder 11-15)
    - Doctoral dissertation materials, 1971-1974 (Folder 11: 5-14)
      Includes notes, drafts, collected articles and clippings
    - Articles, 1966-2000 (Folder 12: 1-11)
    - Articles, 1966-2000 (Contd.) (Folder 13: 1-9)
    - "Demokratiia i sotsializm,", 1974 (Folder 13: 10)
    - "Čacovnik,", 1979 (Folder 13: 11)
    - "Yugoslav Paradox,", circa 1980 (Folder 14: 1)
    - "The Return of the Grand Inquisitor,", circa 1980 (Folder 14: 2)
    - "Tiraniia i svoboda,", 1986 (Folder 14: 3-10)
    - "Nenauchnye mysli,", 1975, 2005 (Folder 15: 1-4)
  - Periodical articles, 1961-2009 (Folder 15-28)
    - In Serbian, 1961-2009 (Folder 15-22)
      - Circa 1970-1990 (Folder 15: 5)
      - 1961-1964 (Folder 15: 6-9)
      - 1964-1989 (Folder 16: 1-23)
      - 1989-1992 (Folder 17: 1-10)
      - 1993-1999 (Folder 18: 1-12)
      - 2000-2002 (Folder 19: 1-11)
      - 2002-2004 (Folder 20: 1-11)
      - 2004-2006 (Folder 21: 1-11)
      - 2006-2009 (Folder 22: 1-7)
    - In Russian, 1965-2004 (Folder 22-24)
      - 1965-1976 (Folder 22: 8-15)
      - 1979-1988 (Folder 23: 1-12)
      - 1988-2004 (Folder 24: 1-12)
    - In English, 1966-2006 (Folder 25-28)
      - 1966-1984 (Folder 25: 1-15)
      - 1984-1988 (Folder 26: 1-13)
      - 1988-1999 (Folder 27: 1-13)
      - 2000-2006 (Folder 28: 1-2)
    - In Czech, 1966 (Folder 28: 3)
    - In Finnish, 1987 (Folder 28: 4)
    - In French, 1965-1998 (Folder 28: 5)
    - In German, 1976-1993 (Folder 28: 6-11)
    - In Italian, 1971-1972 (Folder 28: 12)
    - In Polish, 1985 (Folder 28: 13)
    - In Spanish, 1980 (Folder 28: 14)
  - Books, 1965-2008 (Folder 28-29)
    - Moscow Summer, 1965 (Folder 28: 15)
    - A Historic Proposal, 1966 (Folder 28: 16)
    - Russian Themes, 1968 (Folder 28: 17)
    - Russishce Themen, 1969 (Folder 29: 1)
    - Underground Notes, 1970 (Folder 29: 2)
      Inscribed to Andrea Schwab
    - Nenauchnye Mysli, 1979 (Folder 29: 3)
    - Human Rights in Yugoslavia, 1986 (Folder 29: 4)
    - Nietzsche in Russia, 1986 (Folder 29: 5)
    - Planetarna Svest, 2001 (Folder 29: 6)
    - Kontinent 3, 2004 (Folder 29: 7)
    - Nenauchne Misli, 2004 (Folder 29: 8)
    - Ponovljene Misli, 2008 (Folder 29: 9)
- Writings about Mihajlov, 1965-2007 (Box 30-33)
  Contains reviews and comments on Mihajlov's writings and political activities.
  Arranged by language and chronologically therein
  - In Serbian, 1965-2009 (Folder 30-32)
    - 1965-1993 (Folder 30: 1-18)
    - 1994-2005 (Folder 31: 1-13)
    - 2006-2009 (Folder 32: 1-7)
  - In Russian, 1966-2000 (Folder 32: 8-17)
  - In Russian, 1966-2000 (Folder 33: 1-16)
  - In German, 1976-1999 (Folder 33: 17)
- Writings by others, 1921-2010 (Box 34-42:)
  Consists of collected literary works and clippings.
  - In Serbian, 1921-2010 (Folder 34-38)
    - Undated (Folder 34: 1)
    - 1921-1980 (Folder 34: 2-21)
    - 1982-1996 (Folder 35: 1-16)
    - 1997-2002 (Folder 36: 1-12)
    - 2002-2003 (Folder 37: 1-9)
    - 2004-2010 (Folder 38: 1-4)
  - In Russian, 1931-2005 (Folder 38-41)
    - Undated (Folder 38: 5-11)
    - 1931-1941 (Folder 38: 12-16)
    - 1946-1975 (Folder 39: 1-12)
    - 1976-1988 (Folder 40: 1-12)
    - 1989-2005 (Folder 41: 1-16)
  - In English, 1947-2004 (Folder 4: 1-21)
  - In German, 1978 (Folder 4: 22)
- Card file, 1970-1985 (Box 43-46)
  Includes index cards with contact information and notes for research and writings.
  Arranged in two groups, notes and contacts
  - Notes for Mihajlov's research projects and writings, 1975-1980 (Folder 43-44)
  - Index cards with contact information, circa 1980 (Folder 45-46)
- Oversize material, 1997-2004 (Box 47)
  Contains scrapbooks and printed matter
  Arranged by format or title
  - Skriveni delovi istorije, Republika, 1998 (Folder 47)
  - Moderna, srpski nacionalni identitet u XX veku, April-May 2001 (Folder 47)
  - Scrapbook by Marina Solov'eva, 1977 (Folder 47)
  - Scrapbook by Andrea Schwab, 2004 (Folder 47)
- Audiovisual and digital materials, 1967-2010 (Box 48-65)
  VHS videocassettes, compact sound cassettes, CDs, and 3.5 inch floppy disks.
  Arranged by format
  - Compact sound cassettes (Folder 48-52)
  - CDs and 3.5 inch floppy disks (Folder 53-54)
  - VHS videocassettes (Folder 55-64)
  - 3.5 inch floppy disks (Folder 65)